welcome to dating with John Breaux Vicki
I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto and Emily in scientifically
study phenomena like mindfulness and
related phenomena like fluency insight
flow mystical experiences transformative
experiences higher states of
consciousness the cultivation of wisdom
and meaning in life so welcome this is
actually of course if you're joining us
for the first time please stay but in
order to catch up check the notes for
this video and you'll see links to
previous lessons and descents just you
know every Monday as a Dharma day every
Monday I teach a new principle that it's
and the principles build on each other
progressively and they give some sort of
experience lecture size so you can
understand it more directly the rest of
the week including today Tuesday through
Friday we meet together we sit I
sometimes do review I'll do a review
today of the material we covered
yesterday because it was a lot of
material I'll do some further review on
Wednesday so every day we meet at the
end of it there is a question and answer
period the QA days tend to be longer on
the dates that we just sit Tuesday
through Friday we always meet at 9:30
est if you have questions the Q&A at the
end is specifically for questions
regarding the practice that I'm teaching
in this course if you have more
encompassing questions about how this
fits into the cultivation of wisdom on
how Buddhism compares to stoicism or how
what this has to do with the cognitive
science of meaning or responding in the
meeting crisis or other things on like
from my other series or my channel then
once a month we have a livestream Q&A
you can ask those types of questions
okay so let's do a bit of review oh I
have one significant announcements this
is very important many of you know that
my techno mage who runs the technology
for me during all this
and tomorrow and it is his most glorious
birthday today so happy birthday - happy
birthday tomorrow
so last time we talked about the way in
which we practice the five factors of
acquiring mindfulness and that is to
befriend our distractions to turn them
into an arena in which we can learn much
much more so if the distractions go from
being what what the name implies
something that distracts us to something
that actually gives us a property for
practicing the five factors and for
learning a lot more about ourselves
because our distractions tend to reveal
some of our mostly deeply ingrained
habits of mind and identity so let's
first of all review the factors and the
order in which we make use of them the
core factor is vigilance and you
practice that with meditative questing
which you may will still want to do
maybe once a week okay meditative
crusting that's the humility of attitude
that exploratory observation that trying
to get below the familiar face of your
experience to have the insight into the
depths of the past enough so you have a
distraction either physical or emotional
or mental you first label the
distraction as always and then you would
apply vigilance to it then sensitivity
sensitivity you've already been
cultivating a bit already when you were
learning how to route you turn all of
the nouns of your experiences all the
snapshots into a flowing movie so for
example in my distraction was the
physical destruction of pain it's not
pain its paining and it's an unfolding
process that keeps having novelty in it
and emergent properties and features and
patterns okay so sensitivities I let it
flow and I flow with it
acuity acuity it's like remember visual
acuity I try to give the analogy I don't
want to everything confuse together I
want to pull apart and you learn this of
course with finding your flow I want to
pull apart all the different kinds of
sensations that I'm getting so what I'm
calling
when I let it flow I can see that
there's tension sensations and there's
heating sensations and there's kind of
that mysterious felt yuckiness at the
core of it and there's a bunch of other
things going on
next is noticing I try to notice the
three the three aspects of reaction my
physical reaction what's my lived body
doing with respect to the pain what's my
one of my emotions doing with respect to
the pain what is my mind doing not so
much what was my mind thinking but how
is it moving how was it sleeping itself
with its temperature
what's its temper so right you do that
with you do that with physical
distractions as I mentioned with
emotional distractions with mental
distractions I recommend it
right with something like thinking you
try and pay attention to properties of
the voice there might be multiple voices
right then none of them might be yours
one of them might be yours etc or if
it's a scene you try to pay attention to
that what's called mental paint that's a
firm term from phosphoryl their block
you know is if you were looking at that
scene as if it was a painting as if you
put step back and looked at painting and
you weren't looking at it what it was
what it was a painting of but what
materials the artists have used to make
it for all three of these distractions
we have three principles of practice if
you go away if you're distracted from
your destruction by a distraction you
forget the whole inquiring mindfulness
exercise and then you return to your
breath I need to go back to basic for
plasma what they submit obvious all we
just go back when you go back to medical
doctor for passing the first okay if you
go away if it goes away all right then
you return to your breath pay very
careful attention to your attitude
because there's a temptation to try and
turn this into a magical practice if
what you're doing is you're trying to
meditate on thinking and the thinking
goes way pay attention to what that
tastes like what does that feel like in
your mind when it's empty like that
moment of emptiness and then return your
attention to your breath if you're into
okay
merely enduring and you can honestly say
I'm not learning because I'm just
enduring I'm just enduring right come
out of the practice come out of it and
mindfully do what you need to do to
alleviate the source of the distraction
and then return I quickly resent to
reboot the whole that return to the past
no more than odd okay
tomorrow I'll review what to do with
hindrances those are the things that
actually prevent you from practicing so
review tomorrow what to do with
hindrances that's the review today for
destructions let's go over one more time
and there's notes in yesterday's lesson
about this vigilance sensitivity acuity
noticing oh and I forgot to do the fifth
one which is reminding reminding is
throughout the other four the vigilance
the sensitivity the acuity and the
noticing reminding is sati remember to
stay in the practice this is a
mindfulness practice this is an
intentional and attitudinal practice
this is not you do not want to get into
theorizing narrating justifying okay you
want to stay in exploratory observation
stay in the quest okay vigilance
sensitivity acuity noticing okay all
right so please make sure you're ready
you're comfortable in your posture
please set your phones to do not disturb
and we will begin when I say begin begin
[Music]
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate with the cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition coming out
of your set as part of your practice it
is how we cultivate integrity so here's
some questions this one is from great
girl Rubinstein my interest seems to be
mostly captured by sensations in my
torso but outside of my Donna and any
tips for maintaining vocal attention
there so try and intend so try to intend
to give priority to the sensations of
emotion the sensations of motion because
you're probably picking up on all other
kinds of sensations and that's good but
I'm talking about losing those we're
talking about in order to keep the
Dunton focal we concentrate on the
sensation of motion there's motion
throughout I get that but this is where
the motion is most pronounced and if you
sort of intend to prioritize ocean so
that it's what you're most vocally aware
of and then as the emotion as far as the
motion right dissipates throughout your
torso that's how your awareness
dissipate so this sort of tightly
calibrated coupling between how much
attention right how much focal attention
you're giving to where there's focal
motion and then that dissipates the more
peripheral attention with the more
peripheral motion here on a gussy ins
the gussets in what about tendinitis as
a distraction well I can speak very
directly to that I have as I mentioned
many years in my ear and in addition to
getting the pain and the pressure and
the vertigo and the nausea
one thing I have is I have constant
ringing in this year on constant loud
ringing and so what that means for me
yes
doing the practice and not trying to
make that go away but accepting the fact
that they'll always be it'll always be a
background thing they'll always be the
ringing in the background of my
awareness for me it doesn't mean that I
don't get into very deep states I do but
I had to accept that right this the the
ringing well it's almost like you know
in addition that you know I'm talking
about others that murmuring all around
the set decide that you know like I
think of it almost like a theater their
center stage and then there's you know
off to the sides in the wings into you
know in addition to the monkey jumping
into wings there is always this ringing
going on in the ribs and if you shift
right if you accept it sort of radically
accept that I'm not I'm not telling you
how to deal with your your your your
health
that's not my that's piece we're talking
how to deal with this experience in the
practice if you can accept that that
that ringing is going to be and give it
a place say okay I acknowledge you
you're going to be in the background
you're going to be that's what that is
what has worked for me and that it's a
very challenging thing and I empathize
and sympathize quite deeply with you but
this is what has worked for me so we'll
do some more questions tomorrow I will
also do some more review tomorrow
tomorrow I will review how to deal with
the hindrances and three refuges again I
want to thank you all for joining I want
to thank my dear friend and techno major
Mar which a man happy birthday once
again and of course my beloved son Jason
who's always here accompanying me and
helping me please subscribe to the
channel to be notified of the next video
remember you can go to links in the
description of this video to previous
lessons you will also find all that
channel as I said lots of videos that
I've given on things like mindfulness
and insight and flow
a mystical experience higher states of
consciousness wisdom enlightenment like
how to respond to the meeting crisis ok
so that's all there I get also in my
that's in the waking to the meeting
crisis and there's also a lot of I get
to have discussions with really why's
that there's two people on voices with
relation you might find that helpful
um as well please share with others
during this class this is my one of the
ways I'm trying to help people during
the crisis and so you could help me by
you can help me to help others by
promoting this discourse as much as
possible
reminder we're doing this every weekday
morning at 9:30 est there's always a Q&A
at the end of each and that once a month
we have the live stream general Q&A so
everyone please continue to practice
member of continuity of practice is more
important than quantity if you honestly
can only sit for five minutes sit for
five minutes and I wish you well thank
you for your time and attention take
care everyone